Hey everyone, Robert Smith here.
At Planet Money, we cover the world of economics, but honestly, most of us at the show have never studied the subject.
I personally keep a giant textbook right next to me on my desk for when I need to look up the difference between monopoly and monopsony.
It's a real problem.
So this July and August, we're trying something new.
We are all going back to class.
It's called Planet Money Summer School.
which now that I hear it doesn't sound as fun as it's gonna be.
So let's do this promo style.
Here we go, Beach Party.
Planet Money Summer School.
All the economics you meant to learn, but didn't get around to.
We will have eight audio classes, one released every Wednesday, featuring our favorite Planet Money stories and lessons from some of the world's greatest and most charming economists.
Economics is not about money.
It's a lens of great power and beauty.
And once you get the fundamental concepts, you will start to see them everywhere.
the news.
A small asteroid had entered the Earth's atmosphere.
At the supermarket.
Nobody wanted to go buy bacon soda because they felt like when they go in and buy the whole shelf of bacon soda that everybody knew what they was doing.
And even the economics of your dating life.
Each time she went home after the date and she would record one memorable detail.
Pothead, touchy, boring.
This guy had four gym memberships.
Amuse your friends, win arguments, throw the words diminishing marginal utility into every discussion.
And if you do some homework and pass the test at the end, we'll even put your name on a Planet Money Diploma-like certificate.
Planet Money Summer School, new episodes every Wednesday this summer.
And then on Fridays, just like always, we'll release a brand new episode on the economic crisis that we're living through right now.